hello and welcome everyone to the active
inference Institute this is our
quarterly Roundtable update number four
in 2022 it's December 14th 2022 and
we're recording and then instantly
premiering this video due to some tech
difficulties
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
this is a recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll follow a video
etiquette for live streams
all right today in the quarterly Round
Table we're going to have three main
sections we're going to give some
updates at The Institute scale then talk
about developments in Education and
Research and finally discuss a little
bit active inference Institute in 2023
however first those who are here let's
go around and say hello and if you would
like one memory or special part of this
year just something you'll kind of take
with you going forward in 2023
whoever wants to go first just go for it
I'm Dave Douglas I was really pleased to
get
praise from Dr Professor Mark soles a
creator of a couple of different major
waves in contemporary psychoanalysis and
Neuroscience
telling us it's going to be a massive
contribution that we are not only
recording our in-depth discussion and
presentation with him but publishing the
transcript which is what I was hoping to
hear
every time we inconvenienced ourselves
and stayed up late to get things out
there that
we're perceived as having an impact
awesome that's great to hear
hey everyone uh
this uh report that we're finished one
another
intensive on system thinking it is not
quite related to the active interns
Theory activity but in a way it helps
our participants to communicate with
each other and move forward
our internal projects and their
own projects
cool
um
so I think for me this year was probably
the funnest part was the um
Quantum stream I really enjoyed that a
lot
um and I think that like releasing the
video transcript for that will be great
and hopefully impactful and I'm looking
forward to doing more Quantum
information related type of work
um in the future and I think that that
that's that that was probably the
funnest
um memory for me
I think uh interested was on
organizational aspects and
transformation
and possibly related to it
in our aspects written's
the to Institute
structure
it's a good
opportunity for next years
all right
thank you let's uh Jump Right In and
just raise your hands whenever you wanna
address something and uh
on we go
well there's so many ways to cover what
happened in the previous years but this
image meme partially suffices so on the
left side we have the active inference
lab ail
and on the right side we have us today
which is the active inference Institute
aii heading into 2023
and we were the active inference lab
from the first days of 2021 till the
middle of 2022.
for about 18 months and since the middle
of 2022 we've been transforming on
multiple levels into the active
inference Institute so some baseball
card statistics
active lab born 2020 aii born in the
middle of 22.
by the end of 2021 we had 133 live
streams we added about 85 or 84 more in
back in 2021 the active inference
ontology was just a terms list today it
includes definitions translations into
many languages and examples
in 2021 the active inference textbook
did not exist yet today we're
continuously delivering Interactive
Learning groups and building an
epistemic niche
in 2021 the active inference Journal
existed only for special events as a
proof of principle and today which we'll
discuss later we're rapidly transcribing
translating augmenting and versioning
transcripts
and in the active block prints project
in 2021 it was just a dream within a
dream and today we're actually
implementing active inference in the cad
cat and there's other rows that could
have been added but just a little
summary
that brings us into our opening section
on updates at the organizational scale
so first related to the formal changes
and updates at The Institute we would
like to welcome and appreciate our
inaugural cohort of the board of
directors which began their work in
November 2022 that's John clippinger
Raphael Kaufman Daniel Friedman Dean
tickles blue Knight and Mike Smith
the board of directors has had their
first meeting and over the about next
month or so the board of directors will
be selecting officers
so we are actively seeking
self-nominations and suggestions for
those who would like to serve in an
officer position president vice
president secretary treasurer
especially with experience in governance
Financial non-profit and education
so just signal interest in a position or
more generally and we will be able to
find a way for you to contribute as soon
as you're ready to in the right way
and we're going to be taking some steps
as a non-profit and as an organization
for example towards tax exempt 501c3
status
developing Partnerships with other
institutions and building our grants
program anyone want to add anything here
the installment of the board of
directors
also allows us to take a look back on
our scientific Advisory Board and those
who served in 2022 so Bradley Alicia
John boyick Matt Brown John clippinger
Scott David Jeff Emmett Chris Fields
Carl friston Rafael Kaufman Anatoly
levinchuk Rosalind Moran Alba Serrano
Carol Van hoof Tim verbellon Swan Webb
and Michael zargham so big appreciations
to all of those who served in the
scientific Advisory Board this year and
were actively soliciting self and aloe
nominations for the scientific Advisory
Board in 2023
and just connect to us via email if
you're interested and we can provide you
the forms
and now we can more clearly delineate
the formal roles of the board of
directors which are to implement
Institute scale formal strategy and
governance specification and oversight
of officers and to apply active
inference at the organizational scale
from the insight and guidance based work
of the scientific Advisory Board and
their roles and functions include the
stewardship of organizational units
Education and Research assisting with
project development at different stages
periodic meetings as a scientific
Advisory Board quarterly as well as
subset meetings with a special uh
interest focus and other areas of
insight and engagement any comments
all right
another helpful view is that of the
chains of creation of The Institute so
these edges reflect Define types of
relationships that are not merely part
whole or compositional but enabling or
Constructor chains
and The Institute is on the far left
here which enables and creates
organizational unit niches the
educational and research organizational
units that enable and facilitate
projects
which then have attention on Project
Specific systems of interest and they're
accompanying working products and so on
anyone want to add any comments on this
systems engineering diagram as it
relates to the Institute
uh so yeah basically this schema is
helping us to manage attention on
specific works or someone is doing
and uh I believe next year we will bring
her more distance Concepts and plays in
different types of modeling
and modeling for definitions of these
different parts of enabling chain
and so we will have opportunity in case
we have some developments in terms of
number of participants
we can manage all organizational work
with support of such attention
management system let's say
all right
carrying on
we're continuing to work in revise on
the logo in brand redesign for The
Institute
so for now we'll just leave it as a gray
box but there's some really exciting and
artistic designs
that we're working with and we're
looking forward to sharing more about
those designs and the designer when the
time is right in the beginning of the
year
okay on to talking about different
modalities of participation
so what previously was referenced by
just saying come participate in the
Institute is now more clearly annotated
as a volunteer program so of course
everyone is always welcome to engage
with asynchronous active inference
Institute materials like live streams
and Publications and everyone is welcome
to join synchronous drop-in meetings and
the Discord
the volunteer program keeps you in the
loop about specific affordances for
contribution and facilitates your
participation across projects and
learning groups so a volunteer is
somebody who wants to take an active
step in their learning and applying of
active inference and maybe focus in on
one or more project and also just make
sure that they're in the loop with high
quality communication about different
affordances to participate
and excitingly that informal Lane for
participation separated out from the
internship program gives us a lot of
expressivity to work with those who want
to have a more accountability and a
higher intensity engagement
so the internship program was mentioned
in the previous Round Table
and after initializing the official
internship program in October of 2022
sorry typo there
we have 12 registered interns who are
currently active and several more will
be beginning in early 2023.
so this was really awesome to be meeting
and connecting with some
Institute participants who have been
around a long time and who are looking
to take the next step in their work as
well as a lot of others who came in
because this idea of an internship which
can be a real formal recognized
contribution was very Salient so the
internship consists of several main
parts the first main part is education
and that active education looks like
joining one or more learning group
specifically the textbook group and the
systems thinking intensives as well as
some self-driven education around
reading and listening
the second component of the internship
is the project-based learning a
contribution to an Institute project
which we're going to go through in the
coming slides and there's a mentorship
in facilitation component such that the
interns and the institute's visions and
goals and preferences are all aligned in
there in action
so this is a great program that we look
forward to really bolstering and caring
forward year after year
any comments on these points
all right and so just to close out the
Institute level section
we've continued to grow across our
social media platforms and
look forward to anyone who wants to
contribute to help develop these
platforms as well
on to the education organizational unit
at your active one of the Keystone
educational aspects of our year for many
of us was the active inference textbook
group
the active inference textbook of par
pazulo and friston was released as an
open source textbook at the end of March
2022 and we were ready to spin up the
first cohort of the textbook group in
May 2022
and now about six months later the first
cohort has completed their study of the
text and they are invited to serve in a
learning assistant role for future
cohorts
in about September through December we
had the second cohort begin the first
half of the textbook and so in January
2023 cohort 2 is going to complete
chapters 6-10 and the third cohort is
going to begin
what we do in the textbook group is
continual deployment of value-added
services and Scaffolding of a shared
epistemic niche of course if somebody
wants to read and work on the textbook
alone they're welcome to
and we also hope to cultivate a space in
the textbook groups that's engaging and
allows people to increase their
familiarity and fluency and rigor of
understanding of active inference
through using questions and developing
discourse through using the active
inference ontology and weaving the
ontology through their thinking and also
to develop their mathematical bases
whether that's thinking about the
fundamentals of statistics and linear
algebra and base theorem or whether
people are interested in a more advanced
work like connecting the dots between
different formalisms so it was an
awesome year we had probably 50
um around there participants who were
active in different ways and who also
got activated into some other projects
so we just encourage you whether you're
listening to this early enough to join
cohort 3 in January 2023 or whether
you're listening later we'll still be
offering this and other textbook groups
so if you want to learn and learn well
together then the textbook group is
going to be a unique and special
opportunity anything that people want to
add
all right
let me add something
um it was very nice how it was brought
from ontology for using for this value
added services
so the work what was done with ontology
and I think it's mostly because of the
tool the code but
anyway
for an augmenting this work of the
textbook in a group and having such
affordances in terms of like meta data
or quick access for some additional
information
it's really brings
more value for educational process we
visit textbook it's like make it
Interactive
agreed there can be a lot to look at and
go through which is only what we should
expect
but the structure of the learning
environment
asynchronously and synchronously is
simply not possible to offer or derive
alone so again we hope it's something
like a center of gravity for people who
want to be proactive and in this type of
scientific and educational space really
catalyze their learning
onto the live streams and the
educational functions of them in the
fourth quarter of 2022 we had just an
amazing set of guests and focal paper
discussions we had guests in the math
stream related to category theory in the
organization stream relating to strategy
and governance
in the model streams related to
branching time active inference and the
pi mdp package
and guests in the guest streams related
to radical inactivism math artificial
intelligence and biological intelligence
and we featured three papers in the
discussions around the paper streams and
that was a worked example of the
Bayesian mechanics of classical objects
in live stream 49.
interceptionist modeling allostasis as
control in live stream 50 and canonical
neural networks perform octave inference
in 51 and each of these series were
exceptional
the authors joined and we had a DOT zero
crew each time who was really committed
to understanding and communicating the
material
so there are many ways you can help us
co-create special and engaging live
streams in 2023
you are always welcome to participate in
preparing and enacting live streams
whether you do or don't want to actually
join a live stream
it's also great to self-nominate or
suggest or introduce somebody to join
forestream
it's also a great opportunity to
collaborate on a DOT zero background and
context video that's a great way to have
your studying leveraged and Amplified by
thousands of folds your notes will not
just live on your own computer they'll
exist in a space where others can
benefit from them
and feel free to just join those regular
live stream meetings to learn more any
more comments
one ongoing series that is capturing the
last few slots and is ongoing is the
governing continuous transformation book
stream blue wanna add any words on that
sure so I think
um I was inspired by the transformation
of the lab to The Institute and by
joining the board of directors to study
governance in a more formal way so we
have this book that
is a recent text that reframes
governance in the light of active
inference so we undertook study Tyler
sullenberg and myself and Daniel have
been participating in the dot zero
versions of the bookstream and we're
doing one video per chapter of the text
and we will get together for some
discussions at the end of each book
section so if you want to participate
either in joining the dot zero or in a
discussion of the material presented in
the text get in touch because we would
love to have other perspectives and
additional feedback
thanks
well as alluded to earlier by Dave these
live streams are not just a dead end
at the Active inference Journal we pick
up where the live stream ends
and our goal is to increase the
accessibility and indexability of live
streams and audio visual material
so to give a summary of just an instance
like a case of the journal
we took the transcript of guest stream
16 with Mark solms on Consciousness as
Precision optimization here's a
screenshot with Mark myself Stephen and
Dave having those live streams and then
through the development of a journal
utilities GitHub repo and a tremendous
amount of scripts and expertise from
Dave
the outcome with some automated and some
manual components is an augmented
transcript that contains different
features it can be as plain as what
comes off of the transcription
artificial intelligence it can be as
rich as
hyperlinked and interactive with
embedded images translations and so on
and as of today
December 14th we have dois for all of
the paper live streams that occurred
during 2022 and now we're working
through the backlog of previous streams
and so what that looks like on the live
stream Coda page is you'll find the
event name the date it was live streamed
the video watch link the title and link
to the paper and information on the
guests you'll also find that there are a
link to the slides
a link to the transcript
a DOI provided if you want to cite it
and also a link to the GitHub where that
series can be versioned so people can
fix typos in a decentralized way that's
incremented and trackable they can also
add simulations and all kinds of other
contributions that people might want to
do so that the threat of these
discussions stays alive
Dave it was great work and a fun time
this year what would you like to add or
provide
well the
we're just getting on there has in in a
few very technical and very high impact
field notably virology
and public health there has been a huge
push internationally across disciplines
to get
Word level phrase level
um conceptual graph level access to all
researchers
it's a lot of material but it is a small
fraction of all of the scholarly
activity uh I think even in that field
the
um
the presentation the ReUse of spoken
material is still pretty minor and
um between the various text repositories
the different uh open science
initiatives and active inference
Institute I think just
continuing to push to make
particularly interdisciplinary and
transdisciplinary
ongoing real-time scholarship the norm
over the next
few years will really pay off
tremendously there's a lot of legal
battles that are going to be getting
worse folks that want to
take possession take ownership of the
entire Genome of every organism and
charge you to know anything uh in my
opinion criminal active criminally evil
activity is being run through legal
systems and
um
uh common law one hopes that simply
overwhelming this with virtuous activity
is going to help to make that much less
of a pathology that's
afflicting species and other species
wow
from transcription to The Meta crisis
and back
it's uh really been educational though
and we all know just in the unrecorded
private conversations we have and in the
seminars and in the meetings that we've
had over the previous years enabled by
video conversation
amazing things are said and amazing
perspectives are shared by experts
beginners all kinds of experts and
people with their own lived experience
and yet the best we can do in many
situations is linked to a video and
sometimes not even that so to have all
of the transcripts and an increasing
number of captions and their
translations in a searchable and
trainable and accessible form
is again as Dave mentioned we hope that
this can become a
continuous development
leaving a huge amount of functional
products in the niche and the costs are
not high and it is more possible than
ever truly within the last several
months there were developments in speech
and text processing that changed our
ways of working so that was just quite
exciting to have set out on this path
years ago and see so much of it evolve
in the last few months
Alex or anyone else
yeah
it's actually a
transformational project and for
institute because it was in the
beginning of the year it was like a
dream to have all
videos in transcripts
and this project
I believe several technology driving
with Dave's expertise
give us these pictures when we actually
have
transcripts and have a backlog when we
can improve and having this Text corpus
but and yeah
we are as Institute we are on Frontier
in terms of using tools that we have
from AI developments and always
text Forum content
will
will be developed in different ways this
all different kinds of new technologies
awesome all right
carrying on
Yvonne want to describe the work in the
systems engineering intensive
yeah sure
so the next year we start a new
intensive for four weeks for beginning
and this type of intensive whale
uh mostly for our
internals
but we are hoping to and welcoming all
other who are interested in systems
engineering approach
we will going in through the concepts
and mostly on role Concepts like
they are
the corner store in the systems
engineering habits very helpful to
negotiating within the projects
so
besides all of the theory part we will
have
a practical part and
we'll solve some cases like you can see
here with the concepts and
examples from the real life it's help it
will help to understand
the
systems engineering approach more
precisely
awesome so it's going to be four weeks
synchronous with also asynchronous work
and learning
want to add a few more details here
yeah
here is uh we'll provide the RSVP form
for your
uh for your confirmation and
here we provide some specific States and
if you are available for your specific
days
and if you have more questions you can
easily reach us out forever
uh email
awesome this like active inference it's
a framework that helps us think shapes
and scaffolds our attention and
affordances
and also Mary's well with active
inference as we continue to think about
the Institute
and all of its attendance systems as
something like a synthesis of active
inference with systems engineering
want to summarize this slide
yeah I just want to start for free as
one so
this this time we will uh we'll provide
uh the linkage between Edison for
instance system thinking and we can
publish some
uh some small review on what's the
entire linkage linkage is now and how we
consider it now
yes yeah and this part this type of
activity is part of
the educational problem of Institute for
augmented intelligence
and you can hear you can see here the
link of The Institute and part of the
courses that are available
in English it's uh
partly translated by
autonomous
translation so it could be somehow not
uh so play they have so play in English
but anyway it's very
uh useful content to uh
moving any projects
for us to the their purposes whatever
research projects is or industrial or
whatever projects you are
uh you are a logical
excellent
all right any final comments on
education
it's been quite an educational year
those who are in the game
and listen to some conversations joined
a few read some papers
scan the social medias State abreast of
what was happening and changing in our
field it was incredible actually when
people look back on 2022 and plus or
minus several years from now there's so
much happening and so much to learn that
those who choose to act first and step
into The Fray are already learning
at least for myself more than we thought
was possible
on to the research projects so here
we're just going to more cursorally
overview some research projects because
they're all in progress with a lot of
different outcomes and just join the
meetings for these projects when we pick
back up in 2023. so in the active
inference ontology We are continuing to
develop the ontology fleshing out the
terms list as well as Associated
definitions examples counter examples
and so on
as well as the translations into
different languages and with the
mathematics this is what facilitates an
engineering grade approach to the active
inference knowledge ecosystem
in the active block fronts project
primarily with a development work of
Jacob we've continued to explore
computational implementations of active
inference primarily in Python and Pi mdp
but also in a few other ways and this
will be a continued uh active Locus in
2023 we had a paper and a poster and
maybe some other outcomes from this
project in 2022 and we're going to make
it even more this year
in robotics and embodied we have JF
facilitating a really unique project and
direction
it's been great to have jf's experience
with the physical and the metaphysical
one might say and the way that they come
together in these
Society of Lego entities but also a
great project and offering where those
who want to learn more about symbolic
active inference and Robotics
can connect with JF and work on this
really unique project
and then there's a few other projects
seeds that we're looking to activate as
needed which is the graphical interface
project asking what is it like to learn
and apply active inference from a visual
and Intermodal perspective
highlighting accessibility and rigor
and in the cognitive agent modeling
project where we're doing research
analysis to understand the similarities
and differences amongst different
cognitive modeling Frameworks such as
active inference and others so that in
the future when we say
well we study attention this way we can
also flesh that out by saying and these
other common Frameworks that are used in
field one two three study attention this
way and this framework doesn't use
attention and so this is why we think
that active inference could do better
than this framework in this place and
help this framework in this way
and then
we have the individual research projects
which just reflect the research projects
that driven individuals are the
champions of
and uh they're not always going to be
carried out using the onft ontologies
narratives formal documents and tools of
the Institute
which is to say it's not necessarily a
coded document owned by the active
inference Institute with an open source
dedication but it could be
and these research projects have been
very fruitful and engaging and it's been
an honor to connect with so many diverse
individuals who are making it happen in
their own way and sometimes working
amidst the traditional research
structures but needing an outlet that's
not what they have and other times
coming from outside of traditional
research structures and that's just
really special to see at the Institute
just to give a little
um one more detail on active block
prints with some memes and road maps
our main conceptual Focus this year was
understanding the multi-agent case for
active inference simulations
understanding the dimensionality and
some of the constraints and processes
associated with multi-agent simulations
will then let us revisit different pomdp
partially observable Markov decision
process modeling schemes and heuristics
and we think of active block for
instance having two primary departments
on the theoretical side there's a host
of questions related to different
functionalities of models and
computational implementations as well as
exciting areas like Quantum active
inference and on the applied side there
are various settings and use cases where
we can really start to make that last
mile between a general purpose package
and a domain-specific use case
any
final comments on Research
all right
well there are so many ways to talk
about what comes next and I'm hoping
that in early 2023 we'll be
communicating those to all of you
here's just one synthesis visualization
to help those who might want to see
we are Niche bound
on all sides and we wouldn't want it any
other way
at The Institute scale we have a renewed
understanding and structural enablements
with the board of directors in a formal
governance role and a scientific
Advisory Board as a broader Global
cohort of individuals who want to be
scientific informal advisors
and we're continuing to develop our
grants and partnership programs as well
as make advancements on the bolts
domains business operational legal
Technical and social
within the Institute we have two
organizational units the edu active
educational unit and the Research Unit
at the research and education unit level
we're interested to have stewarded
development by those who have that kind
of vision and capacity to share and
generally to increase participation
quality and quantity and increase our
capacity to model projects for example
in 2022 we were able to develop an
improved meta model or a template for
live streams which enabled us to
increase the quantity and quality of the
live streams and we look forward to
doing those kinds of meta modeling
approaches across other working products
and system of Interest types
and The Last Mile where the work is
actually done where the epistemic rubber
hits the pragmatic road is in the
projects where we hope and expect and
prefer to see sustained participation
from Global participants volunteers and
interns
and it's through the projects and the
services that they project back into the
niche
by which we actually close the loop
through continual action inference and
service so here's the live streams going
out through a data Channel here's the
transcripts leaking out of a GitHub repo
here's somebody translating the ontology
into a new language so that all the
previous projects can be empowered
here's a script coming out here's some
other ambassadorship and so this is just
one way we are
representing to you and to ourselves
what the Institute is and what it does
in a complex and changing niche
any multi-level thoughts that you
fellows would like to share
the last two was like uh thinking
assistance
okay
2022 was a year of
foreign
telligence generated images and text for
many so
thought we'd throw out a few computer
generated not Designer generated logos
but they're pretty cool we made many
more and had fun times I think all of us
dialoguing and next year in the active
diffusion project we'll have a lot more
to say about this
well
what would a good understanding enable
of The Institute and our niche
what are some unique predictions and
implications of our work what are the
next steps for free energy principle and
active inference and The Institute
what are the goals of this researcher
work and what are you still curious
about
a closing round from everyone as we
have our final live stream of the year
I want to know more about this active
diffusion project and where can I sign
up
sounds way fun
that's my closing thought
catechism incoming
so it's like closing Roundtable for this
year I believe you can save it is was
quite a journey
and we redefine in a lot of stuff in
terms of our own understanding about
understanding of niche and adopting our
structure
uh to be able to
be more and more
valuable for
for different communities for different
possible
into the sounds and stakeholders so next
year's
look
bright
thank you Yvonne and Dave
yeah for me the more most exciting thing
is our internship and I'm really looking
forward to
how people from different domains
will
[Music]
learn more about
active inference and bring their
perspective into this year
and
get it back
our perspective
this is will be very awesome I think
thank you Dave
that's extraordinary the the range of
interests and expertise that have come
through uh some folks are you see their
faces every week some folks are working
hard but behind the scenes
um there have been folks that
dropped in a lot
um a year or two ago we haven't seen for
a while I suspect they are greatly
enriched and by this collaboration and
that saw some of them will come back and
uh uh whether we see them or not they're
using what they've learned both the soft
and the hard skills in enriching other
there it is
wow totally agree with all of that
I may have to sneak in
a final separate stream to review one
slide per guest stream or paper because
we truly had such a range of guests
and for those who
tune in
asynchronously or those who join the
meetings
it's
it's been incredible the The Bravery and
the honesty
and the authenticity
that Learners and researchers all around
the world
brought to this little corner
of the internet
in its truly earliest days will always
be remembered
okay
till next time
thank you right